<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="buildspans" module="max" category="Analysis">
	<digest>Assembles and analyzes temporal spans of musical note data using hierarchical dictionaries, deferred rating heuristics, and multi-threaded coordination</digest>
	<description>
		The &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; object is an advanced real-time musical analysis external for Max/MSP. It is designed to ingest stream-like note events (such as timestamp-score pairs) and dynamically group them into contiguous sequences of musical bars called &lt;strong&gt;spans&lt;/strong&gt;. A bar is a musical time interval of a specific duration, defined either by a local override value or retrieved dynamically from an external &lt;code&gt;buffer~&lt;/code&gt;.
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		The internal working memory is maintained within a hierarchical &lt;code&gt;t_dictionary&lt;/code&gt; called &lt;code&gt;building&lt;/code&gt;, using key pathways formatted as &lt;code&gt;palette::track_offset::bar_timestamp::property&lt;/code&gt;. Each bar in this dictionary stores parallel lists of absolute note timestamps (&lt;code&gt;absolutes&lt;/code&gt;), note-level ratings (&lt;code&gt;scores&lt;/code&gt;), a calculated mean score (&lt;code&gt;mean&lt;/code&gt;), the high-precision offset at the bar's creation (&lt;code&gt;offset&lt;/code&gt;), and the active palette (&lt;code&gt;palette&lt;/code&gt;). A lightweight Active Registry maintains track-to-palette combinations, preventing expensive linear scans during discovery and flushing operations.
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;1. Offset Resolution Hierarchy and Quantization&lt;/h3&gt;
		To correctly assign incoming notes to their proper temporal grid, the object uses a two-tier offset resolution hierarchy:
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tier 1 (Dictionary Lookup):&lt;/strong&gt; If notes have already been received for a given span, the object retrieves the precise high-precision offset stored with the first bar of that span in memory. This ensures all subsequent notes in the span align to the exact same temporal grid, even if the global offset has moved.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tier 2 (Effective Global Offset):&lt;/strong&gt; If no active span is found in memory, the object falls back to the current global offset. If no global offset has been set (value is &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;= 0.0&lt;/code&gt;), the object enters &lt;strong&gt;Ephemeral Auto-Initialization&lt;/strong&gt; mode, where the note's own calculated timestamp acts as the offset for that specific processing cycle without mutating the global state.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
		Using the resolved &lt;code&gt;actual_offset&lt;/code&gt;, the relative note position is calculated as:
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;code&gt;relative_timestamp = calc_timestamp - actual_offset + loop_start&lt;/code&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		And quantized into a bar timestamp by rounding down to the nearest multiple of the bar length:
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;code&gt;bar_timestamp = floor(relative_timestamp / bar_length) * bar_length&lt;/code&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;2. Span Termination and Discontiguity Checks&lt;/h3&gt;
		A span will automatically close and flush to the outlets under the following conditions:
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discontiguity (Gap Detection):&lt;/strong&gt; If an incoming note or a manual global offset update creates a temporal gap larger than a configured threshold (by default, &lt;code&gt;2.0 * bar_length&lt;/code&gt;, mathematically representing exactly one full bar of absolute silence), the current span is closed and flushed. An optimized lookup avoids redundant key traversals when no pruning or discontiguity occurs.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating-Based Deferred Pruning:&lt;/strong&gt; When a new bar is started, the object evaluates the previous bar against the existing span using a deferred rating heuristic (see below). If the criteria are met, the previous bar is pruned from the span, and the remaining portion of the span is immediately terminated.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manual Flush / Bang:&lt;/strong&gt; A &lt;code&gt;bang&lt;/code&gt; or explicit &lt;code&gt;flush&lt;/code&gt; message instantly ends and outputs open spans.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;3. Deferred Rating-Based Pruning Mechanics&lt;/h3&gt;
		Rather than assessing bars instantly, the object defers evaluation until a new bar receives its first note. The rating of any span is calculated as the lowest bar mean score in that span multiplied by the total number of bars in the span:
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;code&gt;Rating = lowest_mean_score * bar_count&lt;/code&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		The object compares the hypothetical rating of the span with the last bar included (&lt;code&gt;Rating_with&lt;/code&gt;) against the rating of the span excluding the last bar (&lt;code&gt;Rating_without&lt;/code&gt;). The span is pruned and ended before the last bar if either condition is met:
		&lt;ol&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Including the last bar decreases the overall span rating: &lt;code&gt;Rating_with &amp;lt; Rating_without&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The individual rating (mean score) of the last bar on its own is strictly greater than the rating of the combined span if it were included: &lt;code&gt;Mean_last_bar &amp;gt; Rating_with&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ol&gt;
		When pruning is triggered, the pruned bar's dictionary keys are surgically removed (using an optimized $O(K)$ single-pass linear traversal) and re-initialized as a standalone span, while the previous contiguous bars are terminated and output.
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;4. Concurrency, Deferral, and Crucible Binding&lt;/h3&gt;
		To guarantee high-precision scheduling and prevent audio dropouts (such as the "Audio Thread Grip" phenomenon where dictionary allocations block the audio thread), &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; provides multiple execution models:
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deferred Execution (@defer 1):&lt;/strong&gt; Automatically redirects all state-changing operations and dictionary management from high-priority threads (such as Scheduler or Audio) to the Max Main (UI) thread.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asynchronous Worker Thread (@async 1):&lt;/strong&gt; Offloads all heavy computations, dictionary allocations, and span-building operations to a dedicated background worker thread.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direct Crucible Binding (@bind &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;):&lt;/strong&gt; Binds directly to a &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; object via scripting name. When bound, &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; calls &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; functions directly to synchronize data structures and bypasses its own standard outlets for ultimate efficiency. If both objects are in &lt;code&gt;@async&lt;/code&gt; mode, they safely share the same background worker thread to enforce strict operation ordering.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
	</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Analysis</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Transcription</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Thread-Safe</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="list/bang/clear">
			<digest>Inlet 1 (Leftmost): Note data, bang to flush, clear state, or configuration messages</digest>
			<description>
				Accepts note data as:
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- A two-float list: &lt;code&gt;[calc_timestamp, score]&lt;/code&gt; representing the note's millisecond timestamp and rating.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- A three-float list: &lt;code&gt;[calc_timestamp, score, store_timestamp]&lt;/code&gt; where the third value is the absolute physical timestamp preserved in the dictionary, and the first value is used for bar quantization.
				&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Also accepts:
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- &lt;code&gt;bang&lt;/code&gt;: Triggers a global flush of all open spans for all tracks and palettes, resetting the cached local bar length to zero.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- &lt;code&gt;clear&lt;/code&gt;: Instantly resets all internal states, frees all allocated memory, empties dictionaries, and resets the local bar length to zero.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- &lt;code&gt;set_bar_buffer [symbol]&lt;/code&gt;: Specifies the name of the external &lt;code&gt;buffer~&lt;/code&gt; to read the default bar length from.
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="list/float">
			<digest>Inlet 2: Global offset timestamp and loop start</digest>
			<description>
				Receives high-precision temporal anchors to calculate relative note positions:
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- A single float sets the persistent global offset (in milliseconds).
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- A two-float list &lt;code&gt;[offset, loop_start]&lt;/code&gt; sets both the global offset and the loop start compensation (used in the relative timestamp calculation).
				&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Setting this offset can trigger track duplication or discontiguity checks across active spans.
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="3" type="int">
			<digest>Inlet 3: Active track number</digest>
			<description>Receives an integer that sets the active track ID for subsequently received notes.</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="4" type="symbol">
			<digest>Inlet 4: Active palette name</digest>
			<description>Receives a symbol representing the current palette name, partitioning note streams into independent analysis scopes.</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="5" type="float">
			<digest>Inlet 5 (Rightmost): Local bar length</digest>
			<description>
				Sets a local bar length override in milliseconds. If set to &lt;code&gt;0.0&lt;/code&gt; or less, the override is disabled, and &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; will retrieve the bar length from the external &lt;code&gt;buffer~&lt;/code&gt; (configured via &lt;code&gt;set_bar_buffer&lt;/code&gt;) and cache it.
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="list">
			<digest>Outlet 1 (Leftmost): Span of bar timestamps</digest>
			<description>
				When a span completes and is flushed, outputs a list of integers representing the quantized bar timestamps that constitute the span.
				&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This outlet is bypassed entirely if the object is successfully bound to a &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; object via the &lt;code&gt;@bind&lt;/code&gt; attribute.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="int">
			<digest>Outlet 2: Track ID</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs the track identifier associated with the completed span.
				&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This outlet is bypassed entirely if the object is successfully bound to a &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; object via the &lt;code&gt;@bind&lt;/code&gt; attribute.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="3" type="anything">
			<digest>Outlet 3: Detailed bar dictionary data</digest>
			<description>
				When a span completes, this outlet outputs individual messages containing the detailed properties of each bar in the span. The messages are output with hierarchical selectors formatted as &lt;code&gt;track::bar::property&lt;/code&gt; (such as &lt;code&gt;absolutes&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;scores&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mean&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;offset&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;palette&lt;/code&gt;).
				&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This outlet is bypassed entirely if the object is successfully bound to a &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; object via the &lt;code&gt;@bind&lt;/code&gt; attribute.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="4" type="anything">
			<digest>Outlet 4 (Rightmost): Real-time logging and visualization</digest>
			<description>
				If logging (&lt;code&gt;@log 1&lt;/code&gt;) or visualization (&lt;code&gt;@visualize 1&lt;/code&gt;) is enabled, this outlet outputs detailed status information and JSON-formatted state snapshots.
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist />
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="list">
			<digest>Process a note or offset update</digest>
			<description>
				Processes note data on Inlet 1, or offset updates on Inlet 2.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- Inlet 1 expects &lt;code&gt;[calc_timestamp, score]&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;[calc_timestamp, score, store_timestamp]&lt;/code&gt;.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- Inlet 2 expects &lt;code&gt;[offset, loop_start]&lt;/code&gt; or a single float &lt;code&gt;[offset]&lt;/code&gt;.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="float">
			<digest>Process numeric input</digest>
			<description>
				Redirected based on the inlet:
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- Inlet 2: Sets the persistent global offset.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- Inlet 3: Updates the active track ID.
				&lt;br /&gt;
				- Inlet 5: Updates the local bar length override.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<digest>Process integer input</digest>
			<description>
				Equivalent to float input. Typically used on Inlet 3 to set the active track ID.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="bang">
			<digest>Flush all active spans</digest>
			<description>
				Immediately ends and outputs all currently active spans across all tracks, palettes, and offsets. It also resets the cached local bar length to zero to force a fresh buffer query on the next note.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="flush">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="track-id" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Flush a specific track</digest>
			<description>
				Immediately ends, prunes, and outputs all currently open spans for the specified track ID across all active palettes.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<digest>Reset internal state and memory</digest>
			<description>
				Completely resets the analysis engine. Clears the working &lt;code&gt;building&lt;/code&gt; dictionary, resets the active registry, zeroes out the global offset, resets the local bar length to zero, and empties the thread-safe circular log history.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="set_bar_buffer">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="buffer-name" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Configure external bar length buffer</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the name of the Max &lt;code&gt;buffer~&lt;/code&gt; object to read the default bar length from (defaults to "bar" if not configured).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="log">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Enable or disable logging in real-time</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the &lt;code&gt;@log&lt;/code&gt; attribute dynamically.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="visualize">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Enable or disable real-time visualization data output</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the &lt;code&gt;@visualize&lt;/code&gt; attribute dynamically.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="bind" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>Bind to crucible instance</digest>
			<description>
				Specifies the scripting name (varname) of a target &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt; object in the Max patch.
				When bound, &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; bypasses its standard outlets (Outlets 1, 2, and 3) and instead invokes &lt;code&gt;crucible&lt;/code&gt;'s internal functions directly for data communication. This eliminates high-overhead message passing and maintains strict data alignment. If both objects are configured for asynchronous execution, they automatically share the same background worker thread to enforce strict FIFO ordering.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable verbose logging and automatic file reports</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), outputs step-by-step mathematical calculations, offset resolutions, discontiguity assessments, and pruning outcomes to the rightmost outlet.
				&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Furthermore, whenever a completed or pruned span consisting of &lt;strong&gt;three or more bars&lt;/strong&gt; with a &lt;strong&gt;negative rating (&amp;lt; 0.0)&lt;/strong&gt; is processed, the object automatically generates a detailed textual report file. These logs are saved in a &lt;code&gt;logs/&lt;/code&gt; directory created adjacent to the compiled external object file, utilizing platform-appropriate cross-platform path resolution APIs (Win32 or POSIX) to guarantee compatibility.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="visualize" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable real-time visualization output</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), &lt;code&gt;buildspans&lt;/code&gt; serializes its internal state changes, ratings, and track configurations into JSON formatted packets and outputs them via the rightmost outlet to synchronize with connected external visualizer applications.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="defer" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Defer dictionary operations to the Main thread</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), intercepts incoming note and offset events and defers their processing to the Max Main (UI) thread. This keeps the high-priority Audio and Scheduler threads completely free from the overhead of memory allocations and complex dictionary modifications, preventing jitter and dropouts in audio-rate tasks.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="async" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable thread-agnostic asynchronous background execution</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), instantiates and offloads all analytical computations, rating evaluations, and dictionary mutations to a dedicated background worker thread.
				&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				This provides full protection against the "Audio Thread Grip" phenomenon by ensuring that high-priority threads never block on mutexes or undergo heavy calculations. If bound to a crucible object that also has asynchronous mode enabled, both objects seamlessly coordinate on the same background worker thread to ensure operations are processed in the exact order they were received.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="crucible" />
		<seealso name="rebar" />
		<seealso name="notify" />
		<seealso name="whichoffset" />
		<seealso name="growbuffer~" />
		<seealso name="stemversion" />
		<seealso name="createproject" />
		<seealso name="dict" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>