<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="smartloop~" module="max" category="Analysis">
	<digest>Finds the longest interval of below average bars in a music transcript</digest>
	<description>
		The `smartloop~` object binds to an external dictionary containing a music transcript. Every 999 milliseconds, it scans the dictionary to identify the longest continuous time span composed of "below average" bars. This periodic polling ensures that the loop boundaries are pre-calculated and can be released with minimum latency when a ramp event is detected.

		Classification is based on the `rating` key found in each bar, averaged across all tracks for each unique timestamp:
		1. The object calculates an averaged rating for each unique bar timestamp across all tracks.
		2. The object calculates the global average rating as the mean of these per-timestamp averaged ratings.
		3. Timestamps with an averaged rating &gt; global average are considered **above average**.
		4. Timestamps with an averaged rating &lt;= global average are considered **below average**.

		The object identifies the start and end of a time span (in milliseconds) that represents the greatest distance between the beginning of any below average interval and the end of any below average interval, provided there are no above average bars within that interval. Note that spans in the transcript are ignored; each bar is judged individually. These pre-calculated values are output from the second and third outlets whenever the audio signal ramp in the first inlet loops left (i.e., its current value is less than its previous value) OR when a significant "jump" in the ramp is detected, OR when the ramp starts again after being exactly 0.0. If the ramp is exactly 0.0 for a full signal vector, both outlets will output 0.0 via a deferred (main thread) call.

		Whenever a loop, jump, or start is detected, a `bang` is also emitted from the first (leftmost) outlet. This `bang` is sent even if the object's output is paused (via an integer 0 in the first inlet), whereas the loop boundaries are gated by the pause state. To prevent feedback loops, the object uses a dual suppression mechanism. First, it uses a standard `suppress` flag to gate the immediate detection while output is being deferred to the main thread. Second, after firing the outlets, the object enters a state where it will explicitly suppress exactly the next detection that happens. This is intended to catch the "echo" jump typically caused by the patch's response to the new loop points. If no such second bang occurs within 99 milliseconds, the object forgets the suppression and returns to normal operation. This 99ms value is arbitrary but works in practice. Note that 0.0 ramp detection (outputting 0.0 boundaries) does NOT produce a bang and does NOT engage the suppression mechanism.

		Jump detection works by monitoring the rate of change (delta) of the input ramp. If the difference between the current delta and the previous delta exceeds the `jump_threshold`, the object identifies this as a discontinuity and triggers the release of the loop boundaries.

		**Note:** Valid start or end points for a loop that are exactly 0.0 are output as 1.0. This ensures that 0.0 is reserved exclusively for when the time ramp is stationary.

		**Note:** Bars with negative timestamps are artificially ignored in all calculations (averaging, global average calculation, and loop identification) as if they did not exist.

		Temporal analysis requires the `bar_length` metadata, which is retrieved from an external `buffer~` named **bar**. If the buffer is not found, the object will periodically attempt to re-bind to it ("kick the reference").
	</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Analysis</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="signal/anything">
			<digest>Inlet 1: (signal) Time Ramp / (int) Pause/Resume / (messages) debug</digest>
			<description>Accepts an audio signal time ramp. When this ramp loops left (i.e., its current value is less than its previous value), makes a sudden jump (see `jump_threshold`), or starts again after being exactly 0.0, the object outputs the current loop boundaries and a bang. If the ramp is exactly 0.0 for a full vector, the object outputs 0.0 from each loop point outlet (deferred to the main thread) without a bang or suppression. Also accepts an integer (0 to pause output from the first two outlets, non-zero to resume) and the 'debug' message.</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="bang">
			<digest>Outlet 1: Loop, Jump, or Start detected</digest>
			<description>Emits a `bang` whenever the input ramp loops left, a jump is detected, or the ramp starts again after being stationary. This outlet fires even when the object is paused. Output is deferred to the main thread for safety and suppression timing.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="float">
			<digest>Outlet 2: Start of longest below average interval (ms)</digest>
			<description>Outputs the beginning timestamp of the longest continuous interval consisting only of below average bars. If the valid start point is 0.0, it is output as 1.0 to distinguish it from the 0.0 ramp state (0.0).</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="3" type="float">
			<digest>Outlet 3: End of longest below average interval (ms)</digest>
			<description>Outputs the ending timestamp of the longest continuous interval consisting only of below average bars. If the valid end point is 0.0, it is output as 1.0 to distinguish it from the 0.0 ramp state (0.0).</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="4" type="anything">
			<digest>Outlet 4: Logging (Optional)</digest>
			<description>If the log attribute is enabled, this outlet provides diagnostic status messages.</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="dictionary-name" type="symbol" optional="0">
			<digest>The name of the external dict object to bind to</digest>
			<description>Specifies the name of the `dict` object that contains the transcript data to be analyzed.</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="debug">
			<digest>Compare ratings with visualizer.py</digest>
			<description>Collects all ratings from the associated dictionary and sends them to the `visualizer.py` script. The visualizer compares these against its own internal state and reports any discrepancies (missing bars or mismatched ratings) back to the Max console and its own console.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<digest>Pause or resume output</digest>
			<description>Sending a 0 to the first inlet pauses the output of loop boundaries from the second and third outlets. Sending a non-zero integer resumes output. Note that the first outlet's `bang` still fires on loop/jump even when output is paused. Internal analysis and logging continue regardless of this state.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="visualize">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the visualize attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `visualize` attribute in real time. When enabled (1, default), the object allows sending debug information to the visualizer.py script.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="jump_threshold">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="threshold" type="float" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the jump_threshold attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `jump_threshold` attribute in real time, which determines the sensitivity for jump detection.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="log">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the log attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `log` attribute in real time. When enabled (1), outputs verbose diagnostic information to the logging outlet.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="visualize" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Visualize Analysis</digest>
			<description>When enabled (1, default), the object allows sending debug information to the visualizer.py script via the 'debug' message.</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="jump_threshold" get="1" set="1" type="double" size="1">
			<digest>Jump Threshold (ms)</digest>
			<description>Sets the sensitivity for jump detection. If the difference between successive ramp deltas exceeds this value (in milliseconds), a "jump" is detected and the loop boundaries are released. Default is 1.0.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Logging</digest>
			<description>When enabled (1), outputs verbose diagnostic information to the third outlet, including minimum, maximum, and average ratings across all bars, the number of bars and spans analyzed, details of the identified looping interval (start, end, and duration), and real-time detection and suppression events for troubleshooting bang emission.</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="crucible" />
		<seealso name="buildspans" />
		<seealso name="rebar" />
		<seealso name="notify" />
		<seealso name="dict" />
		<seealso name="buffer~" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
