<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="analyze~" module="msp" category="Analysis">
	<digest>Performs spectral transience analysis on an audio signal</digest>
	<description>
		The `analyze~` object performs real-time spectral analysis of an incoming audio signal. It utilizes an STFT-based Mel-spectrogram and Spectral Flux to detect transient peaks and calculate various transience-related metrics. The analysis is performed on a 1ms-hop basis and utilizes a background thread for expensive calculations to maintain audio stability.

		This object uses a unified 15.2-second stateful analysis window, ensuring parity with offline Python-based analysis. Transients are detected across four frequency bands (Sub, Bass/Low-Mid, High-Mid, Treble) and assigned a "Resonance Score" based on their historical relationship with other peaks in a 5-second lookback buffer. The adaptive midpoint threshold for peak detection is calculated using a specialized dynamic historical peak-based sub-window.
	</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Analysis</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="signal">
			<digest>Audio Input (signal)</digest>
			<description>Accepts the audio signal to be analyzed.</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="signal">
			<digest>Transport Clock Input (signal)</digest>
			<description>Accepts a signal representing the current transport clock time. This value is buffered and used to provide compensated timestamps for detected peaks. If no signal is connected to this inlet, the object maintains backwards compatibility and omits the clock value from its output.</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="list">
			<digest>Peak Scores [(clock), band, score]</digest>
			<description>Outputs a list whenever a transient peak is detected. If a signal is connected to the second inlet, the list contains three elements: [compensated clock value, band index, transience score]. If no signal is connected, it outputs the legacy two-element list: [band index, transience score].</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="float">
			<digest>Bar Length (ms)</digest>
			<description>Outputs the absolute time offset (ms) of the highest peak in the current cumulative history buffer.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="float">
			<digest>Rating Score</digest>
			<description>Outputs the average rating score calculated over the analysis history.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="3" type="float">
			<digest>Standard Deviation</digest>
			<description>Outputs the current standard deviation of the analysis scores.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="4" type="float">
			<digest>Contrast Score</digest>
			<description>Outputs a score representing the spectral contrast detected in the signal.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="5" type="float">
			<digest>Bar Length Stability</digest>
			<description>Outputs a score representing the stability of the rhythmic center. It maintains a histogram of the frequency of "highest peak" positions (Bar Lengths). The output value is the average of the counts for all Bar Length integers observed during the current analysis session. A higher value indicates a more stable rhythmic center.</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="dsp64">
			<digest>DSP method</digest>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<digest>Clear internal state</digest>
			<description>
				Clears the internal historical buffers, including the cumulative transience history and the audio/clock buffers. All calculated metrics (Rating, Standard Deviation, etc.) are reset to their initialized values. If the object is part of a shared group, the shared group's buffer is also cleared.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="group" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>Shared Group Name</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the name of the shared memory group. Objects with the same group name will share a cumulative history buffer, allowing their transience analysis to be context-aware of each other. This enables inter-stream rhythmic reinforcement and global transience density calculations. If no group is specified, the object uses a private buffer. Note: This attribute can only be set during object instantiation.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Log Diagnostics</digest>
			<description>
				Enables or disables detailed diagnostic logging. When enabled (1), internal analysis states, peak detection events, and performance metrics are sent to the rightmost outlet. This is useful for debugging and fine-tuning the analyzer's behavior.
			</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="sounds~" />
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
