<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="stoplight" module="max" category="Data">
	<digest>A data gate and bundler for Max messages</digest>
	<description>The `stoplight` object is a data gate that either passes through incoming messages or queues them based on a control signal. It supports multiple data inlet/outlet pairs. When the control inlet (the rightmost inlet) is 0, messages from Inlet 1 (the leftmost inlet) are passed immediately to Outlet 1, bundled with the most recent messages received on the other data inlets (2 to N). When the control signal is non-zero, incoming messages from Inlet 1 and the current values of the other data inlets are stored together in a FIFO (First-In-First-Out) queue. As soon as the control signal returns to 0, all queued bundles are released in the order they were received, with each bundle's contents sent out their respective outlets in right-to-left order.</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Data</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="anything">
			<digest>Inlet 1 (Hot): Data to be passed or queued.</digest>
			<description>Accepts any Max message. These messages are either passed immediately to the outlet (along with values from other data inlets) or stored in a FIFO queue depending on the state of the control inlet.</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="anything">
			<digest>Inlet 2..N (Cold): Data to be bundled with Inlet 1.</digest>
			<description>The most recent value received on each of these inlets is bundled with any message entering Inlet 1. These inlets do not trigger output themselves.</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="3" type="int">
			<digest>Inlet N+1 (Control): Control Signal (0=pass, non-zero=queue).</digest>
			<description>A control value. When 0, data entering Inlet 1 is passed immediately. When non-zero, incoming data is queued. If a non-zero value changes back to 0, the queue is immediately flushed.</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="anything">
			<digest>Outlet 1..N: Data Outputs.</digest>
			<description>The data outputs from the gate. Each outlet corresponds to a data inlet pair. When a bundle is released, messages are sent out their respective outlets in right-to-left order.</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="extra-pairs" optional="1" type="int">
			<digest>The number of extra data inlet/outlet pairs to add to the default pair (1-9).</digest>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="bang">
			<digest>Pass through bang</digest>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<digest>Pass through int</digest>
		</method>
		<method name="float">
			<digest>Pass through float</digest>
		</method>
		<method name="list">
			<digest>Pass through list</digest>
		</method>
		<method name="anything">
			<digest>Pass through anything else</digest>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist />
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
		<seealso name="rebar" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
