<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="createproject" module="max" category="Utility">
	<digest>Automates the creation of organized project folder structures from a master template</digest>
	<description>
        The <inlinecode>createproject</inlinecode> object streamlines the process of starting new audio projects by enforcing a standardized directory hierarchy and automating the initial setup.
        When triggered, it creates a new directory at a specified destination and recursively copies the entire contents of a pre-defined project template into it.
        <br/><br/>
        <b>Key Features:</b>
        <ul>
            <li>Enforces project creation within a specific root directory (e.g., "[Projects]").</li>
            <li>Recursively copies all template files and subdirectories.</li>
            <li>Automatically updates the "Start In" (working directory) parameter of any copied shortcuts named "analyze_files.py - Shortcut" to match their new location, ensuring analysis tools function correctly from the start.</li>
            <li>Includes a dedicated logging system for tracking the creation and copying process.</li>
        </ul>
    </description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Utility</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Project Management</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="symbol">
			<digest>Project path / Command inlet</digest>
			<description>Accepts the full destination path for the new project as a symbol, or specific messages like 'create' to initiate the process.</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="anything">
			<digest>Logging and Status Outlet</digest>
			<description>Outputs detailed status messages, error reports, and confirmation of copied files when the <at>log</at> attribute is enabled.</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist />
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="create">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="path" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Initiate project creation</digest>
			<description>Triggers the creation of the project at the specified path. The object will verify that the parent folder is named "[Projects]" before proceeding with the recursive copy of the template.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="log">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Toggle logging</digest>
			<description>Sets the <at>log</at> attribute. When set to 1, all internal operations and errors are reported through the first outlet.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Detailed Logging</digest>
			<description>When enabled (1), the object provides granular feedback about every directory created and file copied through its outlet. Useful for debugging template structure or verifying successful project initialization.</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="analyze~" />
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
		<seealso name="crucible" />
		<seealso name="smartloop~" />
		<seealso name="rebar" />
		<seealso name="buildspans" />
		<seealso name="notify" />
		<seealso name="stemversion" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
