<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="doubles~" module="msp">
	<digest>Vocal alignment using DTW and WSOLA</digest>
	<description>
		The <o>doubles~</o> object aligns the timing of a subject vocal buffer to match a reference vocal buffer. It uses Mel-Frequency Cepstral Coefficients (MFCC) for feature extraction, Dynamic Time Warping (DTW) for finding the optimal alignment path, and Waveform Similarity Overlap-Add (WSOLA) for artifact-free time-stretching.
	</description>

	<!-- METADATA -->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Vocal</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Alignment</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">DSP</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!-- INLETS -->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="anything">
			<digest>align message</digest>
			<description>Accepts the 'align' message to trigger the offline alignment process.</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!-- OUTLETS -->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="float/bang">
			<digest>Progress and status</digest>
			<description>Outputs progress as a float (0.0-1.0), followed by a 'finished [buffer]' message and a bang when complete.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="list">
			<digest>Function messages</digest>
			<description>Inflection points for the 'function' object. Sends 'clear' followed by individual 'x y' list pairs.</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="anything">
			<digest>Logging</digest>
			<description>Diagnostic logging messages.</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!-- METHODS -->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="reference">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="buffer_name" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the reference buffer</digest>
			<description>Sets the name of the buffer to be used as the timing reference for alignment.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="subject">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="buffer_name" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the subject buffer</digest>
			<description>Sets the name of the buffer containing the audio that will be warped to match the reference.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="destination">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="buffer_name" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the destination buffer</digest>
			<description>Sets the name of the buffer where the aligned audio will be written.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="align">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="start_ms" type="number" optional="1" />
				<arg name="end_ms" type="number" optional="1" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Align subject to reference</digest>
			<description>
				Triggers the background alignment process using the buffers previously specified with the <m>reference</m>, <m>subject</m>, and <m>destination</m> messages. Only the subject buffer is required (set via the <m>subject</m> message); if the destination buffer is unset, it defaults to the subject buffer. If the reference buffer is unset, the object attempts to find a matching reference in the 'stems' dictionary by looking for another buffer with a matching normalized filename (ignoring timestamps and '(doubles)' tags).
				<br /><br />
				The destination buffer will be resized and cleared to match the reference buffer's length if its current length is different. If the destination buffer is already the correct length, it will not be cleared, allowing data from previous alignment operations with different spans to be retained. If the subject is stereo, the destination will be processed as stereo, applying the same timing warp to both channels. Inflection points of the alignment path are output from the second outlet for visualization in a 'function' object.
				<br /><br />
				Optional Arguments:
				<br />• <b>start_ms</b>: The start time in milliseconds for the alignment span.
				<br />• <b>end_ms</b>: The end time in milliseconds for the alignment span.
				<br /><br />
				If a span is specified, the alignment is only performed on that portion of the buffers. The destination buffer will match the full reference buffer length, with the areas outside the aligned span either remaining as they were (if the buffer was already the correct length) or filled with silence (if the buffer was resized).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="undo">
			<digest>Undo the last alignment operation</digest>
			<description>
				Restores the destination buffer to its state prior to the most recent <m>align</m> operation. This includes reverting any resizing that occurred during that operation. Only one level of undo is supported.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="export">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="project_path" type="symbol" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Export processed buffer to disk</digest>
			<description>
				Writes the contents of the last used destination buffer to disk. The export location is constructed as: [project_path]/Samples/Processed/Consolidate/[filename].
				<br /><br />
				The filename is determined by looking up the destination buffer name in a <o>dict</o> object named 'stems'. The retrieved filename is modified by inserting " (doubles) " before the timestamp and updating the timestamp to the current time in [YYYY-MM-DD HHMMSS] format.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!-- ATTRIBUTES -->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="log" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Logging</digest>
			<description>Enable or disable detailed diagnostic logging to the third outlet (Index 2). When enabled, the object will post status updates regarding buffer settings and alignment progress.</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="targetbias" type="double" size="1">
			<digest>Target Bias</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the strength of the "gravity" pulling the alignment towards the ideal DTW position during the synthesis (WSOLA) phase.
				<br /><br />
				When warping audio, the algorithm searches a small range around the target position to find the best waveform match. In silent or quiet regions, waveform correlation can be unreliable. The target bias provides a penalty for candidates far from the target, preventing "drift" in gaps.
				<br /><br />
				Suggested Scale:
				<br />• <b>0.0</b>: No bias. Pure waveform similarity based on normalized cross-correlation.
				<br />• <b>0.01</b> (Default): Subtle timing guide. Recommended for most vocal applications to maintain stability in silent gaps.
				<br />• <b>0.05 - 0.1</b>: Moderate pull. Useful if the alignment feels like it's "wandering" or if the vocal performance is very loose.
				<br />• <b>0.5 - 1.0</b>: Heavy pull. Prioritizes rigid timing over waveform phase-matching (use for rhythmic speech or percussive elements).
			</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!-- SEEALSO -->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="cropsilence~" />
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
		<seealso name="skipsilence~" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
