<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="crucible" module="max" category="Utility">
	<digest>Intelligent Track Data Merging and Comparison</digest>
	<description>
		The `crucible` object is a specialized utility for managing and merging hierarchical track data. It functions by maintaining two sets of data: the "incumbent" (the current ground truth) and the "challenger" (newly arriving data). When a complete span of data is received for a track, `crucible` performs a competitive analysis. If the challenger data is deemed superior based on its "rating" property, it replaces the incumbent data. This object is designed for high-performance data processing in complex musical systems, supporting asynchronous operation via deferral and providing detailed reach and growth metrics.
	</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Utility</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Data</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Dictionary</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="anything/symbol">
			<digest>Primary message stream / Incumbent name</digest>
			<description>
				Accepts all primary control and data messages. This includes 'clear', 'track', 'span', 'reaches', and hierarchical data selectors. Additionally, sending a symbol sets the name of the external incumbent dictionary to be used for comparisons.
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="float">
			<digest>Local Bar Length override</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the local bar length in frames. This value is used for calculating song and track reaches. If set to 0 (default), the object attempts to retrieve the bar length from an external buffer~ named 'bar'.
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="list">
			<digest>Data Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs processed bar data and reach updates.
				1. Bar Data: [palette (symbol), track (long), bar (long), offset (float)] - emitted when a challenger wins or upon certain data updates.
				2. Reach Notification: [- (symbol), track (long), reach (long), -999999.0 (float)] - emitted when a new reach is detected that doesn't exist in the incumbent.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="int">
			<digest>Rebar Status Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs a '1' when the object receives a 'rebar' message and starts executing the rebar functionality, and outputs a '0' immediately after the rebar functionality completes.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="3" type="list">
			<digest>Reach Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs current reach information.
				1. Song Reach: [song (symbol), reach (long)] - monitored continuously and emitted automatically by the dedicated asynchronous worker thread.
				2. Track Reach: [track_id (long), reach (long)] - monitored continuously and emitted automatically by the dedicated asynchronous worker thread.
				3. Minimum Bar: [min (symbol), min_bar (long)] - monitored continuously and emitted automatically by the dedicated asynchronous worker thread.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="4" type="anything">
			<digest>Logging Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs verbose diagnostic and status information. Active only when the 'log' attribute is enabled (1).
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="incumbent-dictionary" type="symbol" optional="1">
			<digest>Initial name for the incumbent dictionary</digest>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="anything">
			<digest>Hierarchical data input</digest>
			<description>
				Accepts messages in the format '[track]::[bar]::[key] [data...]'. This populates the challenger dictionary with attributes for a specific bar on a specific track. Common keys include 'rating', 'palette', 'offset', and 'span'.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="track">
			<digest>Set the target track for subsequent span analysis</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the track ID (long or symbol) to be associated with the next incoming 'span' message.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="span">
			<digest>Trigger span comparison</digest>
			<description>
				Expects a list of bar timestamps. This message triggers the comparison logic: `crucible` compares the challenger bars (specified by the list) against the incumbent bars. If the challenger ratings are higher, the challenger wins and the incumbent is updated.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="reaches">
			<digest>Report current song and track reaches</digest>
			<description>
				Triggers an immediate output of the current song reach, track reaches, and minimum bar values through the third outlet. If the dedicated, asynchronous monitor thread is enabled (@monitor 1), these values are also continuously monitored and emitted automatically upon any changes.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<digest>Reset internal state</digest>
			<description>
				Clears the challenger dictionary, all track reaches, song reach, and internal track context.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="rebar">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="new-bar-length" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Convert transcript to a new bar length</digest>
			<description>
				Converts all of the bar timestamps present in the incumbent dictionary to multiples of the specified new bar length. Re-maps scores and absolutes pairs to the rounded post-conversion bar, updates mean/rating scores, pads contiguous missing multiples, and sends an optimized visualizer update if visualization is enabled.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="replace">
			<digest>Update bar rating for visualization</digest>
			<description>
				Expects a selector and a value, for example: 'replace 4::15972::rating 1.072468'. If the key in the selector is 'rating' and the @visualize attribute is enabled, this message sends a packet to the visualizer to update the specified bar's rating in its local database. This is used for real-time visualization updates and local smartloop analysis within the visualizer.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="log">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the log attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `log` attribute in real time. When enabled (1), status messages regarding comparisons, dictionary operations, and reach updates are sent to the fourth outlet.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="consume">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the consume attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `consume` attribute in real time. When enabled (1), a winning challenger span will trigger a 'deep delete' of the incumbent bars it replaces.</description>
		</method>
		<method name="visualize">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="state" type="int" optional="0" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>Set the visualize attribute</digest>
			<description>Sets the `visualize` attribute in real time. When enabled (1), the current state of the transcript and any new span entries are sent to the external visualization script.</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Verbose Logging</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), status messages regarding comparisons, dictionary operations, and reach updates are sent to the fourth outlet.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="async" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Asynchronous Execution</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), all message parsing, dictionary operations, and span comparisons are conducted on a dedicated background worker thread. This ensures high performance and non-blocking operation relative to the Max scheduler and main thread.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="consume" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Deep Delete</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), a winning challenger span will trigger a 'deep delete' of the incumbent bars it replaces. This also cleans up any other bars that were part of the defeated incumbent spans, preventing "orphaned" data fragments in the dictionary.
				WARNING: This feature is unfinished and will produce unexpected behavior.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="fill" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Padding/Filling</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), any song growth event in either the positive or negative direction automatically pads/fills all other lesser tracks in that direction by copying their existing bars forward or backward to match the longest track length.
				WARNING: This feature is unfinished and will produce unexpected behavior.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="defer" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Main Thread Execution</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), processing of incoming messages and span comparisons is deferred to the Main thread. This is critical for maintaining audio thread stability when dealing with large dictionary structures.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="visualize" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Visualization</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), the current state of the transcript and any new span entries are sent to the external visualization script via TCP on port 9999.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="monitor" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Reaches Monitoring</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1, default), a dedicated background thread continuously monitors the transcript dictionary for any changes in song reach, track reaches, or minimum bar value, and automatically outputs them on Outlet 3. When disabled (0), continuous monitoring is stopped, which allows other dedicated instances of the object to act as the primary monitor in the patch.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="buildspans" />
		<seealso name="skipsilence~" />
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
		<seealso name="stoplight" />
		<seealso name="doubles~" />
		<seealso name="cropsilence~" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
