<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet devhelp="true" type="text/xsl" href="pb-patcher.xsl"?>
<c74object name="crucible" module="max" category="Utility">
	<digest>Intelligent Track Data Merging and Comparison</digest>
	<description>
		The `crucible` object is a specialized utility for managing and merging hierarchical track data. It functions by maintaining two sets of data: the "incumbent" (the current ground truth) and the "challenger" (newly arriving data). When a complete span of data is received for a track, `crucible` performs a competitive analysis. If the challenger data is deemed superior based on its "rating" property, it replaces the incumbent data. This object is designed for high-performance data processing in complex musical systems, supporting asynchronous operation via deferral and providing detailed reach and growth metrics.
	</description>
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Jules</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Utility</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Data</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Dictionary</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="1" type="anything/symbol">
			<digest>Primary message stream / Incumbent name</digest>
			<description>
				Accepts all primary control and data messages. This includes 'clear', 'track', 'span', 'reaches', and hierarchical data selectors. Additionally, sending a symbol sets the name of the external incumbent dictionary to be used for comparisons.
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="float">
			<digest>Local Bar Length override</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the local bar length in frames. This value is used for calculating song and track reaches. If set to 0 (default), the object attempts to retrieve the bar length from an external buffer~ named 'bar'.
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>
	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="1" type="list">
			<digest>Data Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs processed bar data and reach updates.
				1. Bar Data: [palette (symbol), track (long), bar (long), offset (float)] - emitted when a challenger wins or upon certain data updates.
				2. Reach Notification: [- (symbol), track (long), reach (long), -999999.0 (float)] - emitted when a new reach is detected that doesn't exist in the incumbent.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="symbol">
			<digest>Fill Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs the symbol 'fill' whenever the song's total reach grows. This can be used to trigger system-wide updates or notifications.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="3" type="list">
			<digest>Reach Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs current reach information.
				1. Song Reach: [song (symbol), reach (long)] - emitted when song growth occurs or in response to the 'reaches' message.
				2. Track Reach: [track_id (long), reach (long)] - emitted when track growth occurs or in response to the 'reaches' message.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="4" type="anything">
			<digest>Logging Outlet</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs verbose diagnostic and status information. Active only when the 'log' attribute is enabled (1).
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="incumbent-dictionary" type="symbol" optional="1">
			<digest>Initial name for the incumbent dictionary</digest>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="anything">
			<digest>Hierarchical data input</digest>
			<description>
				Accepts messages in the format '[track]::[bar]::[key] [data...]'. This populates the challenger dictionary with attributes for a specific bar on a specific track. Common keys include 'rating', 'palette', 'offset', and 'span'.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="track">
			<digest>Set the target track for subsequent span analysis</digest>
			<description>
				Sets the track ID (long or symbol) to be associated with the next incoming 'span' message.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="span">
			<digest>Trigger span comparison</digest>
			<description>
				Expects a list of bar timestamps. This message triggers the comparison logic: `crucible` compares the challenger bars (specified by the list) against the incumbent bars. If the challenger ratings are higher, the challenger wins and the incumbent is updated.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="reaches">
			<digest>Report current song and track reaches</digest>
			<description>
				Triggers an immediate output of the current song reach and all individual track reaches through the third outlet.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clear">
			<digest>Reset internal state</digest>
			<description>
				Clears the challenger dictionary, all track reaches, song reach, and internal track context.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="log" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Verbose Logging</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), status messages regarding comparisons, dictionary operations, and reach updates are sent to the fourth outlet.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="consume" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Enable Deep Delete</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), a winning challenger span will trigger a 'deep delete' of the incumbent bars it replaces. This also cleans up any other bars that were part of the defeated incumbent spans, preventing "orphaned" data fragments in the dictionary.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="defer" get="1" set="1" type="long" size="1">
			<digest>Main Thread Execution</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (1), processing of incoming messages and span comparisons is deferred to the Main thread. This is critical for maintaining audio thread stability when dealing with large dictionary structures.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="buildspans" />
		<seealso name="skipsilence~" />
		<seealso name="weaver~" />
		<seealso name="stoplight" />
		<seealso name="doubles~" />
		<seealso name="cropsilence~" />
	</seealsolist>
</c74object>
